<!DOCTYPE article PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD Journal Archiving and Interchange DTD v2.3 20070202//EN" "archivearticle.dtd">
<article article-type="research-article" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"><?properties open_access?><front><journal-meta><journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Cell Biol</journal-id><journal-title>The Journal of Cell Biology</journal-title><issn pub-type="ppub">0021-9525</issn><issn pub-type="epub">1540-8140</issn><publisher><publisher-name>The Rockefeller University Press</publisher-name></publisher></journal-meta><article-meta><article-id pub-id-type="pmid">9786951</article-id><article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2132836</article-id><article-categories><subj-group subj-group-type="heading"><subject>Regular Articles</subject></subj-group></article-categories><title-group><article-title>CDO, A Robo-related Cell Surface Protein  that Mediates Myogenic Differentiation </article-title></title-group><contrib-group><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>Jong-Sun</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Mulieri</surname><given-names>Philip J.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>Cary</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Sassoon</surname><given-names>David A.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68">&#x000a7;</xref></contrib><contrib contrib-type="author"><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>Robert S.</given-names></name><xref ref-type="aff" rid="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68">&#x0002a;</xref></contrib></contrib-group><aff id="N0x3ee2d40N0x1e34c68"><label>&#x0002a;</label>Department of Biochemistry and <label>&#x000a7;</label>Brookdale Center for Molecular and Developmental Biology, Mount Sinai School of  Medicine, New York, New York 10029</aff><pub-date pub-type="ppub"><day>19</day><month>10</month><year>1998</year></pub-date><volume>143</volume><issue>2</issue><fpage>403</fpage><lpage>413</lpage><history><date date-type="received"><day>10</day><month>7</month><year>1998</year></date><date date-type="rev-recd"><day>10</day><month>9</month><year>1998</year></date></history><copyright-year>1998</copyright-year><abstract><p>CDO, a member of the Ig/fibronectin type  III repeat subfamily of transmembrane proteins that includes the axon guidance receptor Robo, was identified  by virtue of its down-regulation by the <italic>ras</italic> oncogene.  We report here that one prominent site of <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA  expression during murine embryogenesis is the early  myogenic compartment (newly formed somites, dermomyotome and myotome). CDO is expressed in proliferating and differentiating C2C12 myoblasts and in  myoblast lines derived by treating 10T1/2 fibroblasts  with 5-azacytidine, but not in parental 10T1/2 cells.  Overexpression of CDO in C2C12 cells accelerates differentiation, while expression of secreted soluble extracellular regions of CDO inhibits this process. Oncogenic Ras is known to block differentiation of C2C12  cells via downregulation of MyoD. Reexpression of  CDO in C2C12/Ras cells induces MyoD; conversely,  MyoD induces CDO. Reexpression of either CDO or  MyoD rescues differentiation of C2C12/Ras cells without altering anchorage-independent growth or morphological transformation. CDO and MyoD are therefore  involved in a positive feedback loop that is central to  the inverse relationship between cell differentiation  and transformation. It is proposed that CDO mediates,  at least in part, the effects of cell&#x02013;cell interactions between muscle precursors that are critical in myogenesis.</p></abstract><kwd-group><kwd>myogenesis</kwd><kwd>MyoD</kwd><kwd>CDO</kwd><kwd>Ras</kwd><kwd>cell  differentiation</kwd></kwd-group></article-meta></front><body><p>I<sc>n</sc> vertebrates, the skeletal muscles of the trunk and  limbs arise from the somites. Somites develop from  unsegmented paraxial mesoderm as spheres of columnar epithelial cells that mature into distinct cellular compartments in response to signals from surrounding tissues  (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B5">Christ and Ordahl, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B21">Lassar and Munsterberg, 1996</xref>). The ventral half of the somite develops  into the sclerotome, which has a mesenchymal morphology and ultimately gives rise to vertebrae and ribs. The  dorsal region retains an epithelial morphology and comprises the dermomyotome, which gives rise to skeletal  muscle and dermis. The dermomyotomal cells adjacent to  the neural tube form the myotome, a layer of differentiated muscle cells positioned between the dermomyotome  and sclerotome. The generation of myogenic cells in the  somite is regulated by signals derived from neighboring  axial tissues (neural tube and notocord), including Wnt  family members and Sonic hedgehog, or by less well-defined signals derived from surface ectoderm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Munsterberg et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Stern et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Cossu et al., 1996</xref>).  Determination and differentiation of cells in the skeletal  muscle lineage also requires specific but poorly understood cell&#x02013;cell interactions between muscle precursors,  known as the community effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gurdon, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cossu et  al., 1995</xref>). The cell surface molecules that mediate the  community effect are largely unknown, although cadherins are likely to play a role (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B13">Holt et al., 1994</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B10">George-Weinstein et al., 1997</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B36">Redfield et al., 1997</xref>).</p><p>The earliest known markers that are specific for the  skeletal muscle lineage are the four myogenic basic helix-loop-helix (bHLH)<sup>1</sup> factors MyoD, myogenin, Myf-5, and  MRF4 (for reviews see <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Ludolph and Konieczny, 1995</xref>;  Molkentin and Olson, 1996; Molkentin and Olson, 1996;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Yun and Wold, 1996</xref>). These proteins function in both determination and differentiation of cells in this lineage and  share the remarkable property of being able to activate  the myogenic program in a variety of non-muscle cell  types (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B42">Weintraub et al., 1989</xref>). During differentiation,  myogenic bHLH factors activate muscle-specific genes  and coordinate withdrawal from the cell cycle. They are  also targets of growth factor&#x02013;signaling pathways that negatively regulate myogenic differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Ludolph and Konieczny, 1995</xref>; Molkentin and Olson, 1996; Molkentin and  Olson, 1996; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Yun and Wold, 1996</xref>).</p><p>In cell culture systems, myogenic bHLH factors autoactivate and cross-activate each other's expression, which  likely amplifies and maintains the myogenic phenotype  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Ludolph and Konieczny, 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Molkentin and Olson,  1996<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Molkentin and Olson, 1996<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Yun and Wold, 1996</xref>).  Also present in the regulatory regions of many muscle-specific genes are sequences that bind myocyte enhancer  binding factor-2 (MEF-2) family proteins (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B32">Olson et al.,  1995</xref>). Although MEF-2 factors do not activate myogenesis alone, they interact physically and genetically with  myogenic bHLH factors to do so (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B27">Molkentin and Olson,  1996<italic>a</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B28">Molkentin and Olson, 1996<italic>b</italic></xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Yun and Wold, 1996</xref>).  Proteins other than myogenic bHLH factors therefore  play a role in the positive feedback mechanisms that regulate the myogenic lineage, which raises the possibility that  molecules that participate in the effects of cell&#x02013;cell interactions during myogenesis could also be components of  this network of regulatory proteins.</p><p>Myogenesis serves as a useful model to understand the  relationship between differentiation and oncogenesis. A  variety of oncogenes and growth factors inhibit differentiation of cultured myoblasts via multiple mechanisms, including transcriptional downregulation of genes encoding  myogenic bHLH factors and posttranslational inhibition  of these factors' myogenic activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Olson, 1992</xref>). Importantly, although cell proliferation and differentiation are  usually mutually exclusive, the transformation- and growth  factor&#x02013;mediated blockade of differentiation of myoblasts  is not simply a consequence of maintaining the cells in a  proliferative state, since this inhibition can occur in the absence of cell division (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Spizz et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Olson et al., 1987</xref>).</p><p>We have recently described a novel member of the Ig  superfamily, designated CDO (for CAM-related/down-regulated by oncogenes; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>). CDO is a  member of a recently identified subfamily characterized  by an extracellular region that contains five Ig-like repeats  followed by three fibronectin type III (FNIII)-like repeats,  a transmembrane segment, and a long cytoplasmic tail.  The other members of this 5 &#x0002b; 3 subfamily are the Robo-like receptors, which are all more closely related to each  other than to CDO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Kidd et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zallen et al., 1998</xref>).  Multiple lines of evidence indicate that the Robo proteins,  of which one has been identified in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>elegans</italic>, and two  each in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, rat, and human, are evolutionarily  conserved axon guidance molecules, most likely serving as  receptors for a CNS midline repellent (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Kidd et al., 1998</xref>;  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zallen et al., 1998</xref>). Rat, mouse, and human forms of CDO  have been isolated, but no function for these proteins has  yet been described.</p><p><italic>cdo</italic> is expressed at very low levels in adult rat tissues,  but at high levels in rat embryo fibroblasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al.,  1997</xref>). <italic>cdo</italic> is transcriptionally downregulated by a variety  of oncogenes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>), many of which are  known to inhibit myogenic differentiation (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Olson, 1992</xref>).  We report here that <italic>cdo</italic> is expressed at high levels during  murine embryogenesis in somites, dermomyotome, and  myotome, as well as in myoblast cell lines. Overexpression  of CDO in myoblasts accelerates differentiation, while expression of secreted soluble forms of CDO block this process. Oncogenic Ras inhibits myogenic differentiation in a  fashion dependent on loss of CDO expression, while other  aspects of the transformed phenotype such as anchorage-independent growth, are independent of CDO. Thus,  CDO is a cell surface protein that plays an important role  in myogenic differentiation. We propose that CDO is involved in regulating cell&#x02013;cell interactions between muscle  precursors that are critical in myogenesis. Furthermore,  these results establish that members of the 5 &#x0002b; 3 subfamily  regulate diverse processes that contribute to morphogenesis and differentiation.</p><sec id="MaterialsMethods" sec-type="materials|methods"><title>Materials and Methods</title><sec><title>Isolation of a Mouse cdo cDNA</title><p>A mouse <italic>cdo</italic> cDNA comprising 90 bp of the 5&#x02032; UTR, the full open reading frame, and 122 bp of the 3&#x02032;UTR was isolated by screening a mouse  E10.5 lambda gt11 cDNA library (kindly provided by T. Lufkin, Mount  Sinai School of Medicine) with rat <italic>cdo</italic> as a probe. The amino acid sequence of mouse CDO is 94% identical and 98% similar to rat CDO, and  is 83% identical and 93% similar to human CDO. The GenBank accession  number for mouse <italic>cdo</italic> is <ext-link ext-link-type="gen" xlink:href="AF090866">AF090866</ext-link>.</p></sec><sec><title>In Situ Hybridization</title><p>The mouse <italic>cdo</italic> cDNA described above was subcloned into pBluescript  KS(&#x02212;). This plasmid was linearized, and an anti-sense riboprobe comprising 122 nucleotides of 3&#x02032; UTR and the COOH-terminal 2322 nucleotides  was generated by transcribing from the T7 promoter in the presence of  <sup>35</sup>S- or digoxygenin-labeled nucleotides (used for thin section or whole  mount in situ hybridizations, respectively). A control sense riboprobe did  not generate any signal. Thin-section in situ hybridization was performed  as previously described (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B37">Sassoon and Rosenthal, 1993</xref>). Whole-mount in  situ hybridization was performed as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B12">Henrique et al. (1995)</xref>,  with a slight modification of the bleaching step (6% hydrogen peroxide/ 0.1% Tween 20/PBS for 1 h at room temperature). </p></sec><sec><title>Cell Culture</title><p>C2C12 cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blau et al., 1983</xref>) were cultured in DMEM plus 15% FBS  (growth medium, GM). Cells were induced to differentiate at 80&#x02013;90%  confluence by transferring them into DMEM plus 2% horse serum (differentiation medium, [DM]). C2C12(E) cells were provided by D. Vassilatis  (Merck Research Laboratories, Rahway, NJ), who received them directly  from H. Blau (Stanford University). C2C12(E) cells and the aza-myoblast  lines P2 and F3 (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Davis et al., 1987</xref>) were cultured as described above.  10T1/2 cells were cultured in DMEM plus 10% FBS. Production of recombinant retroviruses and infection of cell lines with pBabePuro (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B29">Morganstern and Land, 1990</xref>) and pBabePuro/<italic>cdo</italic> was performed as described  in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al. (1997)</xref>. Myc-tagged <italic>myoD</italic> and <italic>myogenin</italic> cDNAs (kindly  supplied by A. Lassar; Harvard Medical School) and mouse <italic>cdo</italic> were also  inserted into pBabePuro for production of recombinant viruses. Infected  cultures were selected in medium that contained 5 &#x003bc;g of puromycin per  ml. Soft agar assays and preparative methylcellulose cultures were performed as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kang and Krauss (1996)</xref>. </p></sec><sec><title>RNA and Protein Analyses</title><p>Total cellular RNA was isolated with the TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies, Gaithersburg, MD) according to the manufacturer's instructions.  Northern blot analyses were performed by fractionating total cellular  RNA through agarose-formaldehyde gels, blotting to nylon membranes,  and hybridizing with DNA probes as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Krauss et al. (1992)</xref>.  <italic>myoD</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Davis et al., 1987</xref>), <italic>myogenin</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B46">Wright et al., 1989</xref>) and <italic>myf-5</italic>  probes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Ott et al., 1991</xref>) were used.</p><p>Immunoblot analyses were performed essentially as described in <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang  et al. (1997)</xref>. Cultures were harvested in lysis buffer (10 mM Tris-HCl, pH  7.2/150 mM NaCl/1% Triton X-100/1% sodium deoxycholate/0.1% SDS/1  mM EGTA) containing 1 mM PMSF, 10 ng/ml leupeptin, 50 mM NaF,  and 1 mM sodium orthovanadate. Total proteins were then separated on  SDS-polyacrylamide gels, transferred to nitrocellulose membranes (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content> Life Science, Inc., Arlington Heights, IL), and the membranes  were probed with one of the following antibodies from the indicated  source: anti-myosin heavy chain (MHC) (MF20; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bader et al., 1982</xref>); anti-troponin T (TnT; <named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>, St. Louis, MO); anti-MyoD (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sbct">Santa  Cruz Biotechnology</named-content>, Santa Cruz, CA); anti-myogenin (F5D; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B45">Wright et al.,  1996</xref>); and anti-CDO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>). After extensive washing (with 40  mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0/50 mM NaCl/1 mM EDTA), the blots were reprobed with horseradish peroxidase&#x02013;conjugated secondary antibody, and  specific protein bands were visualized with the ECL chemiluminescent detection system (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="amersham">Amersham</named-content> Life Science, Inc.). Immunostaining for MHC  was performed with the monoclonal antibody MF20 as described by  <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B1">Bader et al. (1982)</xref>. After sequential incubation with biotinylated goat  anti&#x02013;mouse IgG and peroxidase-conjugated streptavidin, cells were  stained with 3,3&#x02032;-diaminobenzidine (<named-content content-type="company" xlink:href="sigma">Sigma Chemical Co.</named-content>).</p></sec><sec><title>CDO Fusion Proteins</title><p>A PCR-derived fragment containing the signal sequence and entire extracellular region of rat CDO was subcloned into the Aptag-2 or Igtag vectors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B2">Bergemann et al., 1995</xref>) to produce CDO-alkaline phosphatase (AP)  and CDO-Fc, respectively. These vectors, which place the fusion proteins  under the transcriptional control of the cytomegalovirus promoter, were  transfected into C2C12(E) cells by the calcium phosphate technique  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B44">Wigler et al., 1978</xref>). 10 &#x003bc;g of each vector was cotransfected with 1 &#x003bc;g of  pBabePuro, and cultures were selected in medium containing 5 &#x003bc;g puromycin per ml. Aptag-4, which encodes a secreted soluble form of AP itself, was used as a control. Secretion of CDO-AP and AP into the medium  of selected cultures was determined by colorimetric assay of AP activity in  conditioned medium (CM) as described by <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B9">Flanagan and Leder (1990)</xref>.  Production of CDO-Fc was determined by immunoprecipitation of CM  with protein A-Sepharose, followed by immunoblot analysis of eluted  proteins with peroxidase-coupled goat anti&#x02013;human IgG.</p><p>To assess the differentiation capacity of cells that secreted these proteins into their medium, we wished to avoid transferring the cells into DM,  because that would remove the secreted protein at the same time the cells  received the differentiation signal. Instead, cells were plated in GM, and  were then held to allow the medium to become depleted of growth factors. Untransfected and AP-expressing C2C12(E) cells differentiated very  efficiently under these conditions (see Results).</p></sec></sec><sec id="Results"><title>Results</title><sec><title>cdo Expression in Early Myogenic Precursors</title><p>Previous studies determined that <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA is expressed  at extremely low levels in adult tissues (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>).  Since many other members of the Ig/FNIII family, including Robo, are expressed and function during development,  <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA expression during murine embryogenesis was  assessed by whole-mount and thin section in situ hybridization. <italic>cdo</italic> is expressed in a variety of tissues in a broad  and complex pattern (P.J. Mulieri, D.A. Sasson, and R.S.  Krauss, unpublished results). The most striking expression  is seen in the somites and neural tube. As early as E8.5,  both the somites and dorsal lips of the neural tube express  high levels of <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> <italic>A</italic>). The somitic expression coincides with formation of the epithelialized somite  since no expression was detected in unsegmented paraxial  mesoderm. All somites were positive for <italic>cdo</italic> expression as  late as E11.5 (data not shown). Thin-section in situ hybridization demonstrated that <italic>cdo</italic> expression is restricted to  the dorsal region of the epithelialized somite (data not  shown), and is maintained in both the dermomyotome and  myotome as the somites matured (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref>, <italic>B&#x02013;E</italic>). The observation of robust expression of <italic>cdo</italic> in the early myogenic  compartment suggests a function during determination or  differentiation of cells in the myogenic lineage. To investigate this possibility further, studies on CDO expression  and function were performed with the well-characterized  C2C12 myoblast cell line.  </p></sec><sec><title>CDO Levels are Regulated during C2C12 Myoblast Differentiation</title><p>C2C12 myoblasts proliferate in serum-rich GM, but when  cultured at a high cell density in mitogen-deficient DM  they withdraw from the cell cycle, express muscle-specific  genes, and fuse to form multinucleate myotubes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B3">Blau et  al., 1983</xref>). Under the conditions used in this study, these  cells expressed detectable levels of myogenin 24 h after  the shift to DM, and produced MHC 24 h after that (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Myotubes began to form 2 d after transfer to DM, and  the majority of cell nuclei were present in large multinucleate myotubes after 4 d in DM. C2C12 cells cultured in  GM expressed <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA and protein regardless of cell  density (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>, lane <italic>1</italic>; and data not shown). The levels of  both the mRNA and protein were transiently but reproducibly increased about twofold 48 h after the cells were  transferred into DM (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>). Interestingly, after 4 d in DM  when the cultures were fully differentiated, CDO protein,  but not mRNA, was dramatically downregulated (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref>).  We have previously demonstrated that, in Rat 6 fibroblasts, CDO is posttranscriptionally regulated by cell&#x02013; substratum adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>). It is possible,  therefore, that differentiation-mediated alterations in the  repertoire of extracellular matrix molecules and receptors  expressed by C2C12 cells plays a role in this phenomenon  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">McDonald et al., 1995</xref>).  </p></sec><sec><title>Overexpression of CDO Induces Precocious  Differentiation of C2C12 Cells</title><p>To investigate the function of CDO during myoblast differentiation, C2C12 cells were engineered to overexpress  CDO. C2C12 cells were infected with control or <italic>cdo</italic>-expressing retroviruses and selected for puromycin resistance; drug-resistant colonies were pooled and examined  for expression of CDO and their ability to differentiate.  The <italic>CDO</italic> virus-infected cells (C2C12/CDO cells) displayed a two- to threefold increase in CDO protein above  the endogenous level produced by control infectants  (C2C12/puro cells; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>a</italic>). Overproduction of CDO had  no effect on the morphology of C2C12 cells, or on their  ability to proliferate in GM (data not shown). When challenged to differentiate, C2C12/puro cells closely resembled the parental line, exhibiting only a few small MHC-positive myotubes after 2 d in DM (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>b</italic>). In contrast,  C2C12/CDO cells formed many large MHC-positive myotubes at the same time point (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>b</italic>). The extent of myogenesis was quantitated by determining the percentage of  nuclei present in myotubes. 2 d after the shift to DM, 17%  of C2C12/puro cell nuclei were found in myotubes,  whereas 59% of C2C12/CDO cell nuclei were in myotubes  (average values determined from four experiments). Consistent with these results, expression of MHC and TnT was  increased in C2C12/CDO cells relative to C2C12/puro  cells as determined by Western blot analysis of cells cultured in DM for 2 d (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>c</italic>). However, expression of  MyoD and myogenin were not increased by overexpression of CDO (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>c</italic>). After 4 d in DM, cultures of both  cell types looked very similar with &#x0223c;80% of their nuclei  present in myotubes. Thus, overexpression of CDO resulted in precocious morphological and biochemical differentiation of C2C12 cells. Similar data were obtained  when CDO was overexpressed in P2 cells, a myoblast line  derived by treatment of 10T1/2 cells with 5-azacytidine  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Davis et al., 1987</xref>), indicating that the effects of CDO  were not restricted to C2C12 cells (data not shown). </p><p>Because C2C12 is a long-established cell line, the effects  of CDO overexpression were also investigated in an additional strain of C2C12 cells (here designated C2C12[E]).  The major differences between C2C12(E) cells and the  strain of C2C12 cells described above are that: (<italic>a</italic>) the  former cells expressed detectable levels of myogenin before the shift into DM; and (<italic>b</italic>) all the events described in  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">2</xref> occurred over 2 d instead of 4 (data not shown).  Overexpression of CDO by two to threefold above endogenous levels (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>a</italic>) led to a striking phenotype in the  C2C12(E) cells: these cells formed myotubes even when  cultured at subconfluence in GM, a condition under which  the parental or control virus&#x02013;infected cells were unable to  do so (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>b</italic>). As might be predicted, this phenotype was  not stable. Continued passage of C2C12(E)/CDO cells resulted in a population of cells that displayed accelerated  differentiation in DM, but no longer formed myotubes in  GM. Thus, overexpression of CDO in highly differentiation-proficient cells was able to override the inhibitory effects of serum on myotube formation transiently. </p></sec><sec><title>Downregulation of CDO Is Required for Ras-mediated  Inhibition of Myogenic Differentiation</title><p>CDO was originally identified as a gene whose expression  was downregulated by v-H-<italic>ras</italic> and other oncogenes (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang  et al., 1997</xref>). Oncogenic Ras blocks differentiation of  C2C12 and other myoblast cell lines by multiple mechanisms, including downregulation of <italic>myoD</italic> and <italic>myogenin</italic>  expression and posttranslational inhibition of the activity  of myogenic bHLH factors (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Konieczny et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar  et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kong et al., 1995</xref>). Furthermore, forced reexpression of MyoD in Ras-transformed C2C12 cells led to  reexpression of endogenous MyoD and myogenin, and  rescued the ability of the transformed cells to differentiate  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Konieczny et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>). We therefore  examined the pattern of CDO expression in Ras-transformed C2C12 cells, as well as the effects of forced expression of CDO on such cells. C2C12(E) cells were infected  with either control or v-H-<italic>ras</italic>-expressing retroviruses, and  were selected for G418 resistance followed by infection  with control or <italic>cdo</italic>-expressing retroviruses and selection  for puromycin resistance. Three cell lines were then used  for further study: C2C12/neo/puro, a double infection control; C2C12/Ras/puro, a transformed cell line; and C2C12/ Ras/CDO, a cell line that expresses both oncogenic Ras  and exogenous CDO. These cells were analyzed for expression of muscle-specific genes at the mRNA and protein levels, for the ability to differentiate, and for transformation-related phenotypes.</p><p>As expected, Ras led to downregulation of both MyoD  and myogenin, although a detectable level of MyoD persisted (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic>). CDO was also strongly downregulated by Ras at both the mRNA and protein levels (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>,  <italic>a</italic> and <italic>b</italic>). Furthermore, C2C12/Ras/puro cells did not express the muscle structural proteins MHC and TnT (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>  <italic>b</italic>), nor did they form myotubes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>c</italic>), even when cultured in DM. In contrast to the other muscle markers,  <italic>myf-5</italic> mRNA, which was expressed at a much lower level  than the other two myogenic bHLH factors, was not regulated by either Ras or culture conditions (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>a</italic>).  </p><p>The forced reexpression of CDO in C2C12/Ras/CDO  cells led to a corresponding reexpression of endogenous  MyoD and myogenin and, when these cells were shifted to  DM, induction of MHC and TnT was restored (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>, <italic>a</italic>  and <italic>b</italic>). Furthermore, C2C12/Ras/CDO cells formed myotubes in DM, although these myotubes were smaller and  less abundant than those found in parental C2C12 cells or  any control virus-infected derivative (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>c</italic>). It should be  emphasized that C2C12/Ras/CDO cells produced a level  of CDO protein that was comparable to the endogenous  level seen in control C2C12/neo/puro cells. Furthermore,  C2C12/Ras/CDO cells reexpressed MyoD, myogenin, MHC,  and TnT at levels only slightly lower than those seen in the  control cells. They also expressed abundant Ras protein,  equivalent to the level seen in C2C12/Ras/puro cells (Fig.  <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Finally, it should be noted that under these conditions (4 d after transfer to DM) there was no difference in  the extent of differentiation between control C2C12(E)  cells and C2C12(E) cells that overexpressed CDO (data  not shown). Similar to MyoD, therefore, reexpression of  CDO is capable of reestablishing the differentiation program in Ras-transformed myoblasts.</p></sec><sec><title>CDO, Like MyoD, Fails to Revert Other Aspects of the  Transformed Phenotype</title><p>Expression of oncogenic Ras in C2C12 cells leads not only  to a block in differentiation, but also to additional responses characteristic of the transformed phenotype; e.g.,  anchorage-independent growth and morphological alterations (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Olson et al., 1987</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>). Forced  expression of MyoD in Ras-transformed C2C12 cells reactivated differentiation, but did not interfere with anchorage-independent growth of the cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>).  We therefore tested the effects of exogenous CDO expression on additional properties of Ras-transformed C2C12  cells. To assess anchorage-independent growth, C2C12/ neo/puro, C2C12/Ras/puro, and C2C12/Ras/CDO cells were  each cultured in soft agar. As expected, C2C12/neo/puro  cells failed to form progressively growing colonies, while  21% of the C2C12/Ras/puro cells formed large colonies  (&#x0003e;0.3-mm diameter). Interestingly, the C2C12/Ras/CDO  cells behaved very similarly to the C2C12/Ras/puro cells,  also forming colonies with an efficiency of 21%. Culturing  Rat 6 fibroblasts in suspension leads to posttranscriptional  downregulation of CDO (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>). To determine  whether the ability of C2C12/Ras/CDO cells to form colonies in soft agar was due simply to loss of stable production of CDO protein, cells were cultured either on plastic  dishes or in medium containing 1.3% methylcellulose,  which permits nearly quantitative recovery of suspended  cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B16">Kang and Krauss, 1996</xref>). Such cultures were then analyzed by Western blotting with antibodies to CDO. As  can be seen in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> <italic>a</italic>, loss of cell substratum adhesion did  not result in loss of CDO protein production in C2C12/ Ras/CDO cells. The ability of these cells to form colonies  in soft agar was therefore not due to a failure to produce  CDO when cultured in semisolid medium. </p><p>C2C12/Ras/puro cells also displayed a typical transformed morphology: the cells were spindly, highly refractile, and disorganized when compared with control C2C12  cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>b</italic> and Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Interestingly, C2C12/Ras/CDO  cells maintained a transformed morphology. C2C12/Ras cells  that expressed retrovirally-encoded MyoD (see below for  a description of these cells) were slightly less rounded than  C2C12/Ras/puro cells, but remained highly refractile and  disorganized (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F5">5</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Similar to the results of <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et  al. (1989)</xref>, these cells formed colonies in soft agar with a  frequency of 22%. Forced reexpression of CDO or MyoD  in Ras-transformed C2C12 cells therefore resulted in very  similar phenotypes. Both genes restored the ability of the  cells to differentiate without significantly affecting their  highly altered morphology or anchorage-independent  growth (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref> and see below). </p></sec><sec><title>Reexpression of MyoD in C2C12/Ras Cells Induces CDO</title><p>One possible interpretation of the striking similarity of the  response of C2C12/Ras cells to exogenous CDO or MyoD  is that CDO can act as an upstream inducer of <italic>myoD</italic> and  <italic>myogenin</italic> expression. The known autoregulatory activity  of myogenic bHLH factors suggests an additional nonmutually exclusive possibility: that CDO is an integral part of  a positive feedback network that controls myogenic differentiation, and is itself regulated by the myogenic program.  To address this question, we expressed myc-tagged MyoD  in C2C12/Ras cells via retroviral infection, and tested the  cells for expression of CDO by Western blot analysis. As  reported previously (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>) and as shown in  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>a</italic>, expression of exogenous MyoD (MyoD* in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>  <italic>a</italic>) induced endogenous MyoD, and when the cells were  cultured in DM, induced the muscle structural protein  TnT. Interestingly, forced expression of MyoD in C2C12/ Ras cells led to expression of endogenous CDO (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>a</italic>),  suggesting the possible existence of a positive feedback  loop between CDO and myogenic bHLH factors. We also  attempted to express myogenin exogenously in C2C12/ Ras cells, but were unable to select cells that produced  more than trace levels of this protein, possibly because  they differentiated prematurely. Nevertheless, the cells  that made a low level of myogenin also restored a small  amount of CDO expression (data not shown).</p><p>The murine embryo fibroblast cell line 10T1/2 can be  converted to MyoD-expressing myoblasts by treatment  with the DNA demethylating agent 5-azacytidine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B41">Taylor  and Jones, 1979</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Davis et al., 1987</xref>). 10T1/2 cells expressed  barely detectable levels of CDO, but two independent  5-azacytidine-induced myoblast lines (P2 and F3) expressed abundant CDO (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>b</italic>). Taken together, the  data presented in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> suggest that <italic>cdo</italic> expression may  be regulated in part by the myogenic program. However,  unlike the four known myogenic bHLH factors, ectopic  expression of CDO in 10T1/2 cells (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>b</italic>) was not sufficient to convert these cells to the myogenic phenotype, as  measured by expression of muscle-specific genes (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref> <italic>b</italic>)  or myotube formation (data not shown).</p></sec><sec><title>Secreted Soluble CDO Inhibits C2C12 Cell Differentiation</title><p>Most members of the Ig/FNIII family bind in homo- or  heterophilic fashion to cell surface proteins on adjacent  cells (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B4">Brummendorf and Rathjen, 1995</xref>). Although CDO  does not appear to mediate cell&#x02013;cell adhesion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al.,  1997</xref>), recombinant soluble fusion proteins that contain  the entire CDO extracellular region coupled to either alkaline phosphatase (AP) or the Fc region of human IgG  (CDO-AP and CDO-Fc, respectively; Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>a</italic>) bound to  the surface of various cell types (data not shown). We reasoned that if CDO exerts its positive effects on myogenic  differentiation via interaction with another protein(s) on  neighboring cells, soluble CDO fusion proteins might  compete with endogenous membrane-bound CDO and  block differentiation. To test this hypothesis, C2C12(E)  cells were stably transfected with expression vectors for  CDO-AP, CDO-Fc, and, as a control, secreted AP alone.  AP activity was easily detected in the conditioned medium  (CM) of the CDO-AP and AP transfectants (data not  shown), and CDO-Fc was detected immunologically in  CM from the CDO-Fc transfectants (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>d</italic>). These cells  were then assessed for their ability to differentiate. </p><p>As shown in Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>b</italic>, cells that expressed AP differentiated robustly (49% of nuclei present in MHC-positive  cells, which were mainly myotubes). In contrast, cells that  expressed either of the CDO fusion proteins differentiated  poorly under the same conditions (12% of nuclei in MHC-positive cells, which were almost exclusively myocytes;  Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>b</italic> and data not shown). Consistent with this result,  Western blot analyses demonstrated that expression of  CDO-AP or CDO-Fc delayed accumulation of the differentiation markers myogenin, MHC, and TnT (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>c</italic>). As  was observed with CDO overexpression (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">3</xref> <italic>c</italic>), however, inhibition by CDO-AP or CDO-Fc was not accompanied by alterations in the levels of MyoD (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>c</italic>). Expression of CDO-AP or CDO-Fc also did not significantly  alter the levels of endogenous CDO (data not shown).  Comparable results were obtained when CM from 293T  cells that had been transiently transfected with CDO-Fc  were added to cultures of naive C2C12(E) cells, but not  when CM from mock-transfected cells was used (data not  shown; see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>d</italic> for production of CDO-Fc by 293T  cells). The inhibition of differentiation by soluble CDO fusion proteins was transient in nature; after several days under differentiation-inducing conditions, the cultures that  expressed CDO-AP or CDO-Fc expressed muscle structural proteins, and had formed MHC-positive myotubes to  nearly the extent observed with the AP-expressing cells  (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F7">7</xref> <italic>c</italic> and data not shown). Expression of soluble secreted CDO fusion proteins therefore significantly delayed, but did not ablate, differentiation. This result is consistent with the notion that soluble CDO exerted its effects  in these cells by competition with endogenous CDO.</p><p>To confirm that inhibition of CDO function interferes  with differentiation, C2C12(E) cells were infected with a  retrovirus harboring a murine <italic>cdo</italic> cDNA in the anti-sense  orientation, or a control virus that lacked a cDNA insert.  Puromycin-resistant colonies were selected, shifted to DM  for 3 d, and the percentage of colonies bearing myotubes  was scored. Approximately 68% of the colonies infected  with the control retrovirus contained myotubes, whereas  only 33% of the colonies infected with the anti-sense <italic>cdo</italic>-expressing virus formed myotubes. Taken together, these  data indicate that endogenous CDO plays an important,  possibly critical, role in myoblast differentiation.</p></sec></sec><sec id="Discussion"><title>Discussion</title><sec><title>CDO Mediates Myogenic Differentiation</title><p>We report here that CDO, a member of the 5 &#x0002b; 3 subfamily of Ig/FNIII repeat&#x02013;containing cell surface proteins  plays a key role in myogenic differentiation. This conclusion is based on the observations that overexpression of  CDO enhances differentiation of myoblast cell lines; that  expression of soluble secreted forms of CDO or antisense  <italic>cdo</italic> vectors inhibit differentiation; and that Ras inhibits  differentiation of myoblasts in a manner dependent on  downregulation of CDO. Additionally, overexpression of  CDO in early passage, highly differentiation-proficient  C2C12(E) myoblasts was sufficient to promote myotube  formation in GM. CDO is the only protein other than a  myogenic bHLH factor able to override a serum- or oncogene-induced block to myogenesis reported to date.</p><p>The enhancement or inhibition of differentiation induced by wild-type or soluble CDO, respectively, occurs  without detectable alterations in the levels of MyoD.  These data suggest that CDO may function by increasing  the activity of MyoD at a posttranslational level. In contrast, reexpression of CDO in C2C12/Ras cells led to induction of <italic>myoD</italic> at the mRNA level. It is worth noting  that C2C12/Ras cells retain low levels of MyoD and Myf-5,  which are presumably kept inactive by poorly understood  posttranslational mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kong et  al., 1995</xref>). One possible explanation for these results is that  CDO overrides or reverses Ras-mediated inhibition of the  remaining low levels of MyoD and Myf-5, leading to activation of the positive feedback loops that regulate expression of myogenic bHLH factors and MEF-2. After a critical threshold concentration of these proteins is achieved,  the ability to differentiate could be reimposed, even in the  presence of activated Ras.</p><p>This feedback mechanism is thought to amplify and  maintain differentiation signals (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B24">Ludolph and Konieczny,  1995</xref>; Molkentin and Olson, 1996; Molkentin and Olson,  1996; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B47">Yun and Wold, 1996</xref>). It is therefore interesting that  expression of exogenous CDO in C2C12/Ras cells led to  induction of MyoD and myogenin, and, conversely, expression of exogenous MyoD in these cells led to induction of CDO. These results indicate that a positive feedback loop exists between CDO at the cell surface and  myogenic bHLH factors in the nucleus, and that CDO  may be an integral component of the myogenic regulatory  network. In this regard, expression of <italic>cdo</italic> in early myogenic precursors (newly formed somites, dermomyotome)  could conceivably play a role in the determination or stabilization of the myogenic lineage, collaborating with or  amplifying signals initiated by Wnt family members and  Sonic hedgehog produced by axial tissues, or by less well-defined signals derived from surface ectoderm (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B30">Munsterberg et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B39">Stern et al., 1995</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B7">Cossu et al., 1996</xref>). This  proposal, though speculative, is consistent with a requirement of muscle precursors within early somites for cell&#x02013;cell  contact in their response to such tissues; i.e., the community effect (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B11">Gurdon, 1988</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B6">Cossu et al., 1995</xref>). Furthermore, the temporal pattern of <italic>cdo</italic> expression in somites  and dermomyotome closely resembles that of <italic>myf-5</italic> (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B34">Ott  et al., 1991</xref>), the myogenic bHLH factor expressed earliest  during embryogenesis and for which a role in determination is strongly indicated (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B26">Megeney and Rudnicki, 1995</xref>).  Nevertheless, CDO expression alone is not sufficient to  convert 10T1/2 cells to a myogenic phenotype. Although  establishing myogenic identity in vivo undoubtedly requires a complex combination of positive and negative signals provided by soluble and surface-bound signaling molecules (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B40">Tajbakhsh and Cossu, 1997</xref>), this negative result  with 10T1/2 cells should be interpreted with some caution  since CDO is apparently unable to bind to itself, and rodent embryo fibroblast cell lines display little binding activity for soluble CDO fusion proteins (J.-S. Kang, P.J.  Mulieri, F. Cole, and R.S. Krauss, unpublished data).  Thus, CDO expressed at the surface of a 10T1/2 cell may  be unengaged, and consequently nonfunctional.</p><p>Regardless of CDO's potential role in determining the  myogenic lineage, it clearly plays a role in differentiation  of committed myoblasts. Because the signal for differentiation of these cells in culture is withdrawal of serum  growth factors, the role of signaling molecules as negative  regulators has received the most emphasis (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Olson, 1992</xref>).  The positive and possibly requisite role of CDO in differentiation suggests that positive signals emanate from the  cell surface as well. Cadherins and N-CAM have both  been implicated in myoblast differentiation and/or fusion,  but whether these molecules serve as actual signal transducers or as adhesion molecules during myogenesis is not  clear (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B35">Peck and Walsh, 1993</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B25">McDonald et al., 1995</xref>). In  principle, CDO could act as a heterophilic CAM, but a signaling role seems more likely since CDO exerted its effects on C2C12 and C2C12/Ras cells without producing  significant alterations in cell aggregation (data not shown). </p></sec><sec><title>CDO and the Inverse Relationship Between  Transformation and Differentiation</title><p>Myogenic differentiation is inhibited by a variety of oncogenes and growth factors via multiple mechanisms (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B19">Konieczny et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B31">Olson, 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kong  et al., 1995</xref>). Oncogenic Ras in particular can inhibit differentiation by transcriptional downregulation of myogenic  bHLH factors, and by multiple modes of posttranslational  inhibition of their activity (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B22">Lassar et al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B18">Kong et al.,  1995</xref>). It is important to note that Ras and specific growth  factors can inhibit differentiation without necessarily forcing the cells to remain proliferative in DM, suggesting the  existence of activities that are specific for this aspect of oncoprotein or growth factor action (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B38">Spizz et al., 1986</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B33">Olson  et al., 1987</xref>). We and others have demonstrated that various responses to Ras can be dissociated from one another,  indicating that distinct combinations of pathways control  individual aspects of the transformed phenotype (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B23">Lloyd et  al., 1989</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B20">Krauss et al., 1992</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B14">Joneson et al., 1996</xref>). It is  striking that CDO and MyoD each reactivate differentiation of C2C12/Ras cells without altering the transformed  morphology or anchorage-independent growth of these  cells. The indistinguishable and highly specific effects of  CDO and MyoD on C2C12/Ras cells strongly reinforces  the notion of a close mechanistic connection between  these proteins. Myogenic bHLH factors, MEF-2, CDO,  and other proteins may comprise a complex network of  factors that auto- and cross-regulate each others' expression and activity during myogenesis. Furthermore, the  ability of Ras to block myogenic differentiation is specifically linked to its ability to disrupt this network. Activated  Raf and a Ras effector loop mutant specific for activation  of Raf (Ras12V,35S; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B43">White et al., 1995</xref>) each downregulate CDO in fibroblasts (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B15">Kang et al., 1997</xref>; J.-S. Kang and  R.S. Krauss, unpublished data), so it is likely that Raf is a  major effector of Ras in this aspect of its actions. Preliminary data also indicate that CDO is not nonspecific in its  ability to override a block to differentiation; TGF&#x003b2;1 inhibits differentiation of C2C12 cells without downregulating  CDO expression, and C2C12/CDO cells are not resistant  to the inhibitory effects of TGF&#x003b2;1 (J.-S. Kang and R.S.  Krauss, unpublished data). </p></sec><sec><title>Functions of the 5 &#x0002b; 3 Subfamily of Ig/FNIII Repeat Proteins</title><p>The 5 &#x0002b; 3 subfamily of Ig/FNIII repeat proteins includes  the Robo-like receptors (one in <italic>Caenorhabditis elegans</italic>,  and two each in <italic>Drosophila</italic>, rats, and humans) that have  been implicated as axon guidance receptors in nematodes  and fruit flies, and likely play a similar role in mammals  (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B17">Kidd et al., 1998</xref>; <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zallen et al., 1998</xref>). This study is the first  to implicate a member of the 5 &#x0002b; 3 subfamily, CDO, in the  myogenic program, and establishes that members of this  subfamily have highly diverse functions. It is intriguing  that the sole 5 &#x0002b; 3 protein in <italic>C</italic>. <italic>elegans</italic> (SAX-3/Robo) is  prominently expressed in muscle, as assessed by a reporter  gene (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B48">Zallen et al., 1998</xref>). <italic>sax-3</italic> may encode multiple functions that have been distributed among several genes that  arose by duplication and divergance during the course of  evolution. It will be interesting to determine if there are  defects in myogenesis in <italic>sax-3</italic> mutants.</p><p>It should also be noted that although CDO participates  in the myogenic regulatory program, <italic>cdo</italic> expression is not  restricted to the myogenic lineage. <italic>cdo</italic> is also expressed at  high levels in the developing nervous system and other tissues during embryogenesis (Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">1</xref> and unpublished data).  Similar to its role in myoblasts, recent experiments indicate that ectopic CDO expression can induce differentiation of a neuroblastoma cell line (F. Cole, J. Feinleib, and  R.S. Krauss, unpublished data). We hypothesize that  CDO may play a role in mediating cell&#x02013;cell interactions  that coordinate appropriate differentiation of specific lineages during embryogenesis.</p></sec></sec></body><back><sec sec-type="display-objects"><title>Figures and Tables</title><fig position="float" id="F1"><label>Figure 1</label><caption><p>Expression of <italic>cdo</italic>  in the early myogenic compartment of the developing  mouse. (<italic>a</italic>) Whole-mount in  situ hybridization of an E8.5  embryo showing strong expression of <italic>cdo</italic> in the dorsal  neural tube (<italic>arrows</italic>) and  somites (<italic>arrowheads</italic>). Expression is present in the  most recently formed somites, and is maintained as  somites develop, but is absent in unsegmented paraxial  mesoderm. (<italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic>) In situ  hybridization of a sectioned E10.5 embryo showing regional expression of <italic>cdo</italic> in somites. (<italic>b</italic>) Bright-field image; (<italic>c</italic>) dark-field images.  (<italic>d</italic> and <italic>e</italic>) Bright-field (<italic>d</italic>) and dark-field (<italic>e</italic>) images of the same section shown in <italic>b</italic> and <italic>c</italic> shown at higher magnification. Note that <italic>cdo</italic>  is expressed at high levels in the dermomyotome (<italic>arrowheads</italic>) and myotome (<italic>arrows</italic>), but is absent from sclerotome (* in <italic>d</italic>).</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f1"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F2"><label>Figure 2</label><caption><p>Expression of CDO in C2C12 myoblasts during differentiation. C2C12 myoblasts were grown to near confluence,  shifted into DM, and harvested at the indicated time points. The  upper panel shows a Northern blot analysis of <italic>cdo</italic> mRNA expression. The ethidium bromide&#x02013;stained gel, displaying the 28S  and 18S ribosomal RNA bands, is shown as a loading control.  The lower panel shows Western blot analyses of CDO, myogenin, and MHC expression as indicated.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f2"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F3"><label>Figure 3</label><caption><p>Overexpression of  CDO enhances differentiation of C2C12 myoblasts.  C2C12 or C2C12(E) cells  were infected with recombinant pBabePuro/<italic>cdo</italic> virus or  pBabePuro virus lacking a  cDNA insert, selected for resistance to puromycin, and  analyzed for expression of  CDO, myotube formation,  and expression of muscle-specific proteins. (<italic>a</italic>) Western  blot analysis of CDO expression by infectants. (&#x02212;) Infection with control pBabePuro  virus; (&#x0002b;), infection with  pBabePuro/<italic>cdo</italic> virus. (<italic>b</italic>) Photomicrographs of infectants. The two panels on the left show cultures of C2C12 infectants stained with a  monoclonal antibody to MHC after 2 d in DM. The two panels on the right show phase-contrast micrographs of C2C12(E) cell infectants cultured in GM. Note that the CDO-overexpressing C2C12(E) cells form myotubes in GM, while the control C2C12(E) infectants  do not. Bar, 250 &#x003bc;m. (<italic>c</italic>) Western blot analyses of muscle-specific proteins expressed by C2C12 cell infectants cultured in G or D medium. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f3a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f3b"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f3c"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F4"><label>Figure 4</label><caption><p>CDO reactivates the differentiation program in C2C12/ Ras cells. C2C12(E) cells were infected with recombinant retroviruses harboring v-H-<italic>ras</italic> or <italic>cdo</italic> (&#x0002b;), or with control viruses (&#x02212;) as  indicated and as described in the text. Cultures were analyzed by  Northern and Western blotting techniques and by microscopy.  (<italic>a</italic>) Northern blot analyses of <italic>cdo</italic>, <italic>myf-5</italic>, <italic>myoD</italic>, and <italic>myogenin</italic>  expression in various infectants cultured in G or D medium. The  ethidium bromide&#x02013;stained gel displaying the 28S and 18S ribosomal RNA bands is shown as a loading control. Note that the endogenous and exogenous <italic>cdo</italic> mRNAs are almost identical in  size. The <italic>myf-5</italic> blot was exposed to film approximately sixfold  longer than the other blots. (<italic>b</italic>) Western blot analyses of Ras,  CDO, MyoD, myogenin, MHC, and TnT levels in various infectants cultured in G or D medium. The identity of the lower band  in the CDO panel is unknown, but is not CDO. The reason for  the downregulation of endogenous MyoD protein in C2C12/Ras/ CDO cells cultured in D medium is not clear, but is not seen with  the control infectants. Downregulation was also observed in  C2C12/Ras cells that expressed exogenous MyoD (see Fig. <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F6">6</xref>).  The expression of low levels of MHC and TnT in the control infectants cultured in G medium (the first lane in <italic>B</italic>) was due to the  high density of these cells when harvested. (<italic>c</italic>) Phase-contrast  photomicrographs of C2C12/Ras/puro and C2C12/Ras/CDO cells  cultured in DM. Note the presence of myotubes in the latter, but  not the former cells. Because the Ras-expressing cells are poorly  adherent and grow to high density in multiple layers, some cells  in each micrograph inevitably appear out of focus. Bar, 250 &#x003bc;m. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f4a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f4b"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f4c"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F6"><label>Figure 6</label><caption><p>Stable expression of MyoD induces CDO. (<italic>a</italic>) Western  blot analyses of MyoD, CDO, and TnT expression is shown for  the indicated infectants cultured in G or D medium. MyoD* indicates retrovirally encoded myc-tagged MyoD; MyoD indicates  endogenous protein. (<italic>b</italic>) Western blot analysis of CDO, MyoD,  and MHC expression in various 10T1/2 cell derivatives. 10T1/2  refers to the parental line; 10T1/2/puro and 10T1/2/CDO are lines  stably infected with control or <italic>cdo</italic> retrovirus, respectively; and P2  and F3 are myoblast lines derived by treatment of 10T1/2 cells  with 5-azacytidine (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="B8">Davis et al., 1987</xref>). CDO expression was analyzed in cells cultured in GM; MyoD and MHC expression was  analyzed in cells cultured for 3 d in DM. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f6a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f6b"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F5"><label>Figure 5</label><caption><p>CDO does not revert anchorage-independent growth  or morphological transformation of C2C12/Ras cells. (<italic>a</italic>) Expression of CDO by C2C12/Ras/CDO cells is not lost when the cells  are cultured in suspension. Western blot analysis of CDO expression is shown for the indicated infectants when cultured on plastic dishes (&#x0002b; adhesion) or in methylcellulose-containing medium  (&#x02212; adhesion). (<italic>b</italic>) Phase-contrast photomicrographs of C2C12/ Ras/puro, C2C12/Ras/CDO, and C2C12/Ras/MyoD cells cultured in GM. Bar, 250 &#x003bc;m. </p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f5a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f5b"/></fig><fig position="float" id="F7"><label>Figure 7</label><caption><p>Secreted, soluble forms of CDO inhibit myogenic differentiation. (<italic>a</italic>) Schematic representation of CDO and the soluble fusion  proteins CDO-AP and CDO-Fc. C2C12(E) cells were stably transfected with expression vectors for CDO-AP, CDO-Fc, or secreted AP  itself, and were analyzed as described below. (<italic>b</italic>) Photomicrographs of cells expressing secreted AP or CDO-AP were cultured under  differentiation-inducing conditions and stained with a monoclonal antibody to MHC. Bar, 250 &#x003bc;m. (<italic>c</italic>) Western blot analyses of MyoD,  myogenin, MHC, and TnT expression in cells expressing the indicated vector cultured for the indicated times under differentiation- inducing conditions (see Materials and Methods for details). (<italic>d</italic>) Western blot analysis of CDO-Fc in CM from stably transfected  C2C12(E) cells and transiently transfected 293T cells.</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f7a"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f7b"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f7c"/><graphic xlink:href="JCB9807055.f7d"/></fig></sec><ack><p>We thank Katja Brose and Marc Tessier-Lavigne for communicating results on <italic>cdo</italic> expression during embryogenesis, Jeff Huang and Kirstin  Lindermayer for their contributions to this study, Andrew Bergemann  and Stave Kohtz for advice and reagents, and Stave Kohtz, Eugenia Spanopoulou, and members of the Krauss lab for comments on the manuscript.</p><p>This work was supported by grants from the National Institutes of  Health (R.S. Krauss and D.A. Sassoon), the Elsa U. Pardee Foundation  (R.S. Krauss), and the American Heart Association-New York Affiliate  (D.A. Sassoon). J.-S. Kang is supported by a fellowship from the Charles  H. Revson Foundation, and by funds from the T.J. Martell Foundation.  R.S. Krauss and D.A. Sassoon are Career Scientists of the Irma T. Hirschl  Trust.</p></ack><ref-list><title>References</title><ref id="B1"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bader</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Masaki</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Fischman</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Immunochemical analysis of myosin heavy chain during avian myogenesis in vivo and in vitro</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1982</year><volume>95</volume><fpage>763</fpage><lpage>770</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6185504</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B2"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Bergemann</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name><name><surname>Cheng</surname><given-names>H-W</given-names></name><name><surname>Brambilla</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Klein</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>ELF-2, a new member of the Eph ligand family, is segmentally expressed in mouse embryos in the region of the hindbrain and newly forming somites</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>4921</fpage><lpage>4929</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7651410</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B3"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Blau</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Chiu</surname><given-names>C-P</given-names></name><name><surname>Webster</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cytoplasmic activation of human nuclear genes in stable heterocaryons</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1983</year><volume>32</volume><fpage>1171</fpage><lpage>1180</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6839359</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B4"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Brummendorf</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Rathjen</surname><given-names>FG</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cell adhesion molecules 1: immunoglobulin superfamily</article-title><source>Protein Profile</source><year>1995</year><volume>2</volume><fpage>963</fpage><lpage>1108</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8574878</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B5"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Christ</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name><name><surname>Ordahl</surname><given-names>CP</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early stages of chick somite development</article-title><source>Anat Embryol</source><year>1995</year><volume>191</volume><fpage>381</fpage><lpage>396</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7625610</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B6"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Donna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivarelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myoblast differentiation during mammalian somitogenesis is dependent upon a community effect</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1995</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>2254</fpage><lpage>2258</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7892257</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B7"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Kelly</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name><name><surname>Tajbakhsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Di Donna</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Vivarelli</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of different myogenic pathways: Myf5 is induced by the neural tube and MyoD by the dorsal ectoderm in mouse paraxial tissue</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1996</year><volume>122</volume><fpage>429</fpage><lpage>437</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8625794</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B8"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a single transfected cDNA converts fibroblasts to myoblasts</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1987</year><volume>51</volume><fpage>987</fpage><lpage>1000</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3690668</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B9"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Flanagan</surname><given-names>JG</given-names></name><name><surname>Leder</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The <italic>kit</italic>ligand: a cell surface molecule altered in steel mutant fibroblasts</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1990</year><volume>63</volume><fpage>185</fpage><lpage>194</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1698555</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B10"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>George-Weinstein</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Gerhart</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Blitz</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Simak</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>N-cadherin promotes the commitment and differentiation of skeletal muscle precursor cells</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>185</volume><fpage>14</fpage><lpage>24</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9169046</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B11"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Gurdon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>A community effect in animal development</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1988</year><volume>336</volume><fpage>772</fpage><lpage>774</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3205305</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B12"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Henrique</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Myat</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Chitnis</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Lewis</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Ish-Horowicz</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Expression of a Delta homologue in prospective neurons in the chick</article-title><source>Nature</source><year>1995</year><volume>375</volume><fpage>787</fpage><lpage>790</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7596411</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B13"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Holt</surname><given-names>CE</given-names></name><name><surname>Lemaire</surname><given-names>P</given-names></name><name><surname>Gurdon</surname><given-names>JB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadherin-mediated cell interactions are necessary for the activation of MyoD in <italic>Xenopus</italic>mesoderm</article-title><source>Proc  Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1994</year><volume>91</volume><fpage>10844</fpage><lpage>10848</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7971972</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B14"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Joneson</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigler</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name><name><surname>Bar-Sagi</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Stimulation of membrane ruffling and MAP kinase activation by distinct effectors of RAS</article-title><source>Science</source><year>1996</year><volume>271</volume><fpage>810</fpage><lpage>812</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8628998</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B15"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Gao</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Feinleib</surname><given-names>JL</given-names></name><name><surname>Cotter</surname><given-names>PD</given-names></name><name><surname>Guadagno</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>CDO: an oncogene-, serum-, and anchorage-regulated member of the Ig/fibronectin type III repeat family</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>203</fpage><lpage>213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9214393</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B16"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kang</surname><given-names>J-S</given-names></name><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ras induces anchorage-independent growth by subverting multiple adhesion-regulated cell cycle events</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>16</volume><fpage>3370</fpage><lpage>3380</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8668152</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B17"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kidd</surname><given-names>T</given-names></name><name><surname>Brose</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Mitchell</surname><given-names>KJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Fetter</surname><given-names>RD</given-names></name><name><surname>Tessier-Lavigne</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Goodman</surname><given-names>CS</given-names></name><name><surname>Tear</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Roundabout controls axon crossing of the CNS midline and defines a novel subfamily of evolutionarily conserved guidance receptors</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>205</fpage><lpage>215</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9458045</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B18"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Kong</surname><given-names>Y</given-names></name><name><surname>Johnson</surname><given-names>SE</given-names></name><name><surname>Taparowsky</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Konieczny</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Ras p21<sup>Val</sup>inhibits myogenesis without altering the DNA binding or transcriptional activities of the myogenic basic helix-loop-helix factors</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>15</volume><fpage>5205</fpage><lpage>5213</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7565669</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B19"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Konieczny</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name><name><surname>Drobes</surname><given-names>BL</given-names></name><name><surname>Menke</surname><given-names>SL</given-names></name><name><surname>Taparowsky</surname><given-names>EJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Inhibition of myogenic differentiation by the H-<italic>ras</italic>oncogene is associated with the down regulation of the MyoD1 gene</article-title><source>Oncogene</source><year>1989</year><volume>4</volume><fpage>473</fpage><lpage>481</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2654809</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B20"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Krauss</surname><given-names>RS</given-names></name><name><surname>Guadagno</surname><given-names>SN</given-names></name><name><surname>Weinstein</surname><given-names>IB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Novel revertants of H-ras oncogene-transformed R6-PKC3 cells</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>12</volume><fpage>3117</fpage><lpage>3129</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1535685</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B21"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Munsterberg</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The role of positive and negative signals in somite patterning</article-title><source>Curr Opin Neurobiol</source><year>1996</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>57</fpage><lpage>63</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8794041</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B22"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Thayer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Overell</surname><given-names>RW</given-names></name><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transformation by activated <italic>ras</italic> or <italic>fos</italic>prevents myogenesis by inhibiting expression of MyoD1</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>58</volume><fpage>659</fpage><lpage>667</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2548731</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B23"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Lloyd</surname><given-names>AC</given-names></name><name><surname>Paterson</surname><given-names>HF</given-names></name><name><surname>Morris</surname><given-names>JDH</given-names></name><name><surname>Hall</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Marshall</surname><given-names>CJ</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>p21<sup>H-<italic>ras</italic></sup>-induced morphological transformation and increases in c-<italic>myc</italic>expression are independent of functional protein kinase C</article-title><source>EMBO (Eur Mol  Biol Organ) J</source><year>1989</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>1099</fpage><lpage>1104</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2663469</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B24"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ludolph</surname><given-names>DC</given-names></name><name><surname>Konieczny</surname><given-names>SF</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Transcription factor families: muscling in on the myogenic program</article-title><source>FASEB J</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>1595</fpage><lpage>1604</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8529839</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B25"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>McDonald</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name><name><surname>Horwitz</surname><given-names>AF</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Adhesion molecules and skeletal myogenesis</article-title><source>Semin Dev Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>105</fpage><lpage>116</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B26"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Megeney</surname><given-names>LA</given-names></name><name><surname>Rudnicki</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Determination versus differentiation and the MyoD family of transcription factors</article-title><source>Biochem Cell Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>73</volume><fpage>723</fpage><lpage>732</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8714693</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B27"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molkentin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combinatorial control of muscle development by basic helix-loop-helix and MADS-box transcription factors</article-title><source>Proc  Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1996a</year><volume>93</volume><fpage>9366</fpage><lpage>9373</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8790335</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B28"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Molkentin</surname><given-names>JD</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Defining the regulatory networks for muscle development</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell Biol</source><year>1996b</year><volume>6</volume><fpage>445</fpage><lpage>453</lpage></citation></ref><ref id="B29"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Morganstern</surname><given-names>JP</given-names></name><name><surname>Land</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Advanced mammalian gene transfer: high titer tetroviral vectors with multiple drug selection markers and a complementary helper-free packaging cell line</article-title><source>Nucleic Acids Res</source><year>1990</year><volume>18</volume><fpage>3587</fpage><lpage>3596</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2194165</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B30"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Munsterberg</surname><given-names>AE</given-names></name><name><surname>Kitajewski</surname><given-names>J</given-names></name><name><surname>Bumcrot</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>McMahon</surname><given-names>AP</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Combinatorial signaling by Sonic hedgehog and Wnt family members induces myogenic bHLH gene expression in the somite</article-title><source>Genes  Dev</source><year>1995</year><volume>9</volume><fpage>2911</fpage><lpage>2922</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7498788</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B31"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Interplay between proliferation and differentiation within the myogenic lineage</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1992</year><volume>154</volume><fpage>261</fpage><lpage>272</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1330787</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B32"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Perry</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Schulz</surname><given-names>RA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Regulation of muscle differentiation by the MEF2 family of MADS box transcription factors</article-title><source>Dev Biol</source><year>1995</year><volume>172</volume><fpage>2</fpage><lpage>14</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7589800</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B33"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name><name><surname>Spizz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Tainsky</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The oncogenic forms of N-<italic>ras</italic> or  H-<italic>ras</italic>prevent skeletal myoblast differentiation</article-title><source>Mol Cell Biol</source><year>1987</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>2104</fpage><lpage>2111</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3600660</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B34"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Ott</surname><given-names>M-O</given-names></name><name><surname>Bober</surname><given-names>E</given-names></name><name><surname>Lyons</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Arnold</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Buckingham</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Early  expression of the myogenic regulatory gene, <italic>myf-5</italic>, in precursor cells of skeletal muscle in the mouse embryo</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1991</year><volume>111</volume><fpage>1097</fpage><lpage>1107</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1652425</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B35"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Peck</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Walsh</surname><given-names>FS</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Differential effects of over-expressed neural cell adhesion molecule isoforms on myoblast fusion</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1993</year><volume>123</volume><fpage>1587</fpage><lpage>1595</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8253853</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B36"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Redfield</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Nieman</surname><given-names>MT</given-names></name><name><surname>Knudsen</surname><given-names>KA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Cadherins promote skeletal muscle differentiation in three-dimensional cultures</article-title><source>J Cell Biol</source><year>1997</year><volume>138</volume><fpage>1323</fpage><lpage>1331</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9298987</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B37"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Sassoon</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Rosenthal</surname><given-names>N</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Detection of messenger RNA by in situ hybridization</article-title><source>Methods Enzymol</source><year>1993</year><volume>225</volume><fpage>384</fpage><lpage>404</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7901737</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B38"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Spizz</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name><name><surname>Roman</surname><given-names>D</given-names></name><name><surname>Strauss</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Olson</surname><given-names>EN</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Serum and fibroblast growth factor inhibit myogenic differentiation through a mechanism dependent on protein synthesis and independent of cell proliferation</article-title><source>J Biol  Chem</source><year>1986</year><volume>261</volume><fpage>9483</fpage><lpage>9488</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3722206</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B39"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Stern</surname><given-names>HM</given-names></name><name><surname>Brown</surname><given-names>AMC</given-names></name><name><surname>Hauschka</surname><given-names>SD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myogenesis in paraxial mesoderm: Preferential induction by dorsal neural tube and by cells expressing Wnt-1</article-title><source>Development</source><year>1995</year><volume>121</volume><fpage>3675</fpage><lpage>3686</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8582280</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B40"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Tajbakhsh</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Cossu</surname><given-names>G</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Establishing myogenic identity during somitogenesis</article-title><source>Curr Opin Genet Dev</source><year>1997</year><volume>7</volume><fpage>634</fpage><lpage>641</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9388780</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B41"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Taylor</surname><given-names>SM</given-names></name><name><surname>Jones</surname><given-names>PA</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple new phenotypes induced in 10T1/2 and 3T3 cells treated with 5-azacytidine</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1979</year><volume>17</volume><fpage>771</fpage><lpage>779</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">90553</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B42"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Weintraub</surname><given-names>H</given-names></name><name><surname>Tapscott</surname><given-names>SJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Davis</surname><given-names>RL</given-names></name><name><surname>Thayer</surname><given-names>MJ</given-names></name><name><surname>Adam</surname><given-names>MA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lassar</surname><given-names>AB</given-names></name><name><surname>Miller</surname><given-names>AD</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Activation of muscle-specific genes in pigment, nerve, fat, lever and fibroblasts cell lines by forced expression of MyoD</article-title><source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source><year>1989</year><volume>86</volume><fpage>5434</fpage><lpage>5438</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2748593</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B43"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>White</surname><given-names>AM</given-names></name><name><surname>Nicolette</surname><given-names>C</given-names></name><name><surname>Minden</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Polverino</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Van Aelst</surname><given-names>L</given-names></name><name><surname>Karin</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Wigler</surname><given-names>MH</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Multiple Ras functions can contribute to mammalian cell transformation</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1995</year><volume>80</volume><fpage>533</fpage><lpage>541</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7867061</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B44"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wigler</surname><given-names>M</given-names></name><name><surname>Pellicer</surname><given-names>A</given-names></name><name><surname>Silverstein</surname><given-names>S</given-names></name><name><surname>Axel</surname><given-names>R</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Biochemical transfer of single-copy eucaryotic genes using total cellular DNA as donor</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1978</year><volume>14</volume><fpage>725</fpage><lpage>731</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">210957</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B45"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Dac-Korytko</surname><given-names>I</given-names></name><name><surname>Farmer</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Monoclonal antimyogenin antibodies define epitopes outside the bHLH domain where binding interferes with protein-protein and protein-DNA interactions</article-title><source>Dev Genet</source><year>1996</year><volume>19</volume><fpage>131</fpage><lpage>138</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8900045</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B46"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Wright</surname><given-names>WE</given-names></name><name><surname>Sassoon</surname><given-names>DA</given-names></name><name><surname>Lin</surname><given-names>VK</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Myogenin, a factor regulating myogenesis, has a domain homologous to MyoD</article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1989</year><volume>56</volume><fpage>607</fpage><lpage>617</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2537150</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B47"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Yun</surname><given-names>K</given-names></name><name><surname>Wold</surname><given-names>B</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>Skeletal muscle determination and differentiation: story of a core regulatory network and its content</article-title><source>Curr Opin Cell  Biol</source><year>1996</year><volume>8</volume><fpage>877</fpage><lpage>889</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8939680</pub-id></citation></ref><ref id="B48"><citation citation-type="journal"><person-group person-group-type="author"><name><surname>Zallen</surname><given-names>JA</given-names></name><name><surname>Yi</surname><given-names>BA</given-names></name><name><surname>Bargmann</surname><given-names>CI</given-names></name></person-group><article-title>The conserved immunoglobulin  superfamily member SAX-3/Robo directs multiple aspects of axon guidance  in <italic>C. elegans. </italic></article-title><source>Cell</source><year>1998</year><volume>92</volume><fpage>217</fpage><lpage>227</lpage><pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9458046</pub-id></citation></ref></ref-list><fn-group><fn><p>The authors dedicate this paper to the memory of Eugenia Spanopoulou.</p></fn><fn><p>Address all correspondence to Robert S. Krauss, Department of Biochemistry, Box 1020, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, New York, NY  10029. Tel.: (212) 241-2177. Fax: (212) 996-7214. E-mail: <email>rkrauss&#x00040;smtplink.mssm.edu</email></p></fn><fn><p>1<italic>. Abbreviations used in this paper</italic>: AP, alkaline phosphatase; bHLH, basic helix-loop-helix; CM, conditioned media; DM differentiation medium;  FNIII, fibronectin type III; GM, growth medium; MEF-2, myocyte enhancer binding factor-2; MHC, myosin heavy chain; TnT, troponin T.</p></fn></fn-group></back></article>


